<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ester hath hang'd Haman: or An ansvvere to a lewd pamphlet, entituled, The arraignment of women With the arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and vnconstant men, and husbands. Diuided into two parts. The first proueth the dignity and worthinesse of women, out of diuine testimonies. The second shewing the estimation of the fœminine sexe, in ancient and pagan times; all which is acknowledged by men themselues in their daily actions. VVritten by Ester Sowernam, neither maide, wife nor widdowe, yet really all, and therefore experienced to defend all.</title>
            <author>Sowernam, Ester.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1188:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ester hath hang'd Haman: or An ansvvere to a lewd pamphlet, entituled, The arraignment of women With the arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and vnconstant men, and husbands. Diuided into two parts. The first proueth the dignity and worthinesse of women, out of diuine testimonies. The second shewing the estimation of the fœminine sexe, in ancient and pagan times; all which is acknowledged by men themselues in their daily actions. VVritten by Ester Sowernam, neither maide, wife nor widdowe, yet really all, and therefore experienced to defend all.</title>
                  <author>Sowernam, Ester.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, 50-51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Snodham] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ester Sowernam is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Swetnam, Joseph.  The araignment of lewde, idle, froward, and unconstant women.</note>
                  <note>The last chapter, signed "Ioane Sharp" (also probably a pseudonym), is in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swetnam, Joseph, fl. 1617. --  Arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and unconstant women --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11435:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11435:1"/>
            <p>Eſter hath hang'd Haman: OR AN ANSVVERE TO a lewd Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>The Arraignment of Women.</hi> With the arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and vnconſtant men, and HVSBANDS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diuided into two Parts.</hi> The firſt proueth the dignity and worthineſſe <hi>of Women, out of diuine Teſtimonies.</hi> The ſecond ſhewing the eſtimation of the Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine Sexe, in ancient and Pagan times; all which is acknowledged by men themſelues in their daily actions.</p>
            <p>VVritten by <hi>Eſter Sowernam,</hi> neither Maide, Wife nor Widdowe, yet really all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore experienced to defend all.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN 8.7.</hi>
               </bibl> He that is without ſinne among you, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at her.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Neque enim lex iuſticior vlla</l>
               <l>—Quam necis Artificem arte perire ſua.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11435:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11435:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Noble, and worthy Ladies, <hi>Gentlewomen, and others, vertuouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, of the Foeminine Sexe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and all others of our Sexe, vpon my repaire to <hi>London</hi> this laſt <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme; being at ſupper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt friends, where the number of each ſexe were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall; As nothing is more v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall for table-talke; there fell out a diſcourſe concerning women, ſome defending, others obiecting againſt our Sex: Vpon which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there happened a mention of a Pamphlet entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Arraignment of Women,</hi> which I was deſirous to ſee. The next day a Gentleman brought me the Booke, which when I had ſuperficially runne ouer, I found the diſcourſe as far off from performing what the Title promiſed, as I found it ſcandalous and blaſphemous: for where the Authour pretended to write againſt lewd, idle, and vnconſtant women, hee doth moſt impudently rage and rayle generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the whole ſexe of women. Wherevpon, I in defence of our Sexe, began an anſwer to that
<pb facs="tcp:11435:3"/>full Pamphlet. In which, after I had ſpent ſome ſmall time, word was brought mee that an Apologie for women was already vndertaken, and ready for the Preſſe, by a Miniſters daughter: Vpon this newes I ſtayed my pen, being as glad to be eaſed of my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended labour; as I did expect ſome fitting perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what was vndertaken: At laſt the Maidens Booke was brought me, which when I had likewiſe runne ouer, I did obſerue, that whereas the Maide doth many times excuſe her tenderneſſe of yeares, I found it to be true in the ſlenderneſſe of her anſwer, for ſhe vndertaking to defend women, doth rather charge and condemne women, as in the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhall appeare: So that wheras I expected to be eaſed of what I began, I do now finde my ſelfe dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charged, as well to make reply to the one, as to adde ſupply to the other.</p>
            <p>In this my Apologie, Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull, and all others of our Sexe, I doe in the firſt part of it plainely and reſolutely deliuer the worthineſſe and worth of women; both in reſpect of their Creation, as in the worke of Redemption. Next I doe ſhew in examples out of both the Teſtaments: what bleſſed and happy choyſe hath beene made of women, as gratious inſtruments to deriue Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and benefits to mankinde.</p>
            <p>In my ſecond part I doe deliuer of what eſtimate women haue been valued in all ancient and moderne times, which I prooue by authorities, cuſtomes, and daily experiences. Laſtly, I doe anſwer all materiall obiections which haue or can be alledged againſt our Sexe: in which alſo I doe arraigne ſuch kind of men,
<pb facs="tcp:11435:3"/>which correſpond the humor and diſpoſition of the Author; lewd, idle, furious and beaſtly diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>This being performed, I doubt not but ſuch as heretofore haue beene ſo forward and lauiſh againſt women, will hereafter pull in their hornes, and haue as little deſire, and leſſe cauſe ſo ſcandalouſly and ſlanderouſly to write againſt vs then formerly they haue.</p>
            <p>The ends for which I vndertooke this enterpriſe, are theſe. Firſt, to ſet out the glory of Almightie God, in ſo bleſſed a worke of his Creation. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to encourage all Noble, Honourable, and worthy Women, to expreſſe in their courſe of life and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they are the ſame Creatures which they were deſigned to be by their Creator, and by their Redeemer: And to paralell thoſe women, whoſe vertuous examples are collected briefly out of the Olde and New Teſtament. Laſtly, I write for the ſhame and confuſion of ſuch as degenerate from wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-hoode, and diſappoint the ends of Creation, and Redemption.</p>
            <p>There can be no greater encouragement to true Nobility, then to know and ſtand vpon the honour of Nobility, nor any greater confuſion and ſhame, then for Nobility to diſmount and abaſe it ſelfe to ignoble and degenerate courſes.</p>
            <p>You are women; in Creation, noble; in Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gracious; in vſe moſt bleſſed; be not forgetfull of your ſelues, nor vnthankefull to that Author from whom you receiue all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11435:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO ALL VVORTHY AND HOPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full young youths of</hi> Great-Brittaine; <hi>But reſpectiuely to the beſt diſpoſed and worthy Apprentifes of LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Opefull and gallant youths of <hi>Great-Brittaine,</hi> and this ſo famous a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. There hath been lately publiſhed a Pamphlet entituled <hi>The Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of lewd, idle froward and inconſtant Women.</hi> This patched and miſhapen hotch-potch, is ſo dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that if <hi>Socrates</hi> did laugh but once to ſee an Aſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce Thiſtles, he would ſurely laugh twice to ſee an idle franticke direct his miſhapen Labours to giddy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded young men: he would ſay, as he did when the Aſſe did eate Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtles, <hi>like lips, like L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſo a franticks writer doth aptly chuſe giddy fauorites.</p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Arraignment,</hi> and my ſelfe, in our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours doe altogether diſagree; he raileth without cauſe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vpon direct proofe. He ſaith, women are the worſt of all Creatures, I prooue them bleſſed aboue all Creatures: He wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that men ſhould abhorre them for their had conditions: I proue that men ſhould honour them for their beſt diſpoſitions he ſaith, women are the cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, I proue, if there be any offence in a woman, men were the beginners. Now, in that it is far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e more woman like to maintaine a right, then it is man like to offer a wrong, I conceiued that I could not erre in my choyſe, if I did direct a labour well intended, to worthy young youths, which are well diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>When you haue paſt your minority, or ſerued your Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips vnder the gouernment of others, when you begin the world
<pb facs="tcp:11435:4"/>for your ſelues, the chiefeſt thing you looke for is a good Wife.</p>
            <p>The world is a large field, and it is full of brambles, bryers, and weedes: If there be any more tormenting, more ſcratting, or more poyſonable weede then other, the Author hath collected them in his lothſome Pamphlet, and doth vtter them to his gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy company.</p>
            <p>Now my ſelfe preſuming vpon your worthy and haneſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, I haue entred into the Garden of <hi>Paradice,</hi> and there haue gathered the choyſeſt flowers which that Garden may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord, and thoſe I offer to you.</p>
            <p>If you belieue our aduerſury, no woman is good, howſoeuer ſhe be vſed: if you conſider what I haue written, no woman is had except ſhe be abuſed.</p>
            <p>If you belieue him that women are ſo bad Creatures, what a dangerous and miſerable life is marriage?</p>
            <p>If you examine my proofes to know directly what women are, you ſhall then finde there is no delight more exceeding then to be ioyned in marriage with a Paraditian Creature. Who as ſhee commeth out of the Garden, ſo ſhall you finde her a flower of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, anſwerable to the Countrey from whence ſhe commeth.</p>
            <p>There can be no loue betwixt man and wife, but where there is a reſpectiue eſtimate the one towards the other. How could you loue? nay, how would you loath ſuch a monſter, to whom <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> poynteth?</p>
            <p>Whereas in view of what I haue deſcribed, how can you but regardfully loue with the vttermoſt ſtraine of affection ſo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable a Iewell.</p>
            <p>Some will perhaps ſay, I am a woman and therefore write more for women then they doe deſerue: To whom I anſwere, if they miſdoubt of what I ſpeake, let them impeach my credit in any one particular: In that which I write, <hi>Eue</hi> was a good woman before ſhe met with the Serpent, her daughters are good Virgins, if they meet with good Tutors.</p>
            <p>You my worthy youths are the hope of Man-hoode, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall poynt of Man-hoode is to defend, and what more man-like defence, then to defend the iuſt reputation of a woman. I know that you the Apprentiſes of this Citie are as forward to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:11435:5"/>the good, as you are vehement to put downe the bad.</p>
            <p>That which is worſt I leaue to our aduerſary, but what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently beſt, that I commend to you: doe you finde the gold, I doe here deliuer you the Iewell, a rich ſtocke to begin the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if you be good huſbands to vſe it for your beſt aduantage.</p>
            <p>Let not the title of this Booke in ſome poynt diſtaſte you, in that men are arraigned, for you are quit by Non-age. None are here arraigned, but ſuch olde fornicators as came with full mouth and open cry to Ieſus, and brought a woman to him taken in adultery, who when our Sauiour ſtoopt downe and wrote on the ground, they all fled away. <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> ſaith, <hi>A man may finde Pearles in duſt,</hi> Pag. <hi>47.</hi> But if they who ſled had ſeene any Pearles, they would rather haue ſtayed to haue had ſhare, then to flye and to leane the woman alone, they found ſome fowle reckoning againſt themſelues in our Sauiours writing, as they ſhall doe who are heare arraigned. And if they dare doe like, as our Sauiour had the womans accuſers, <hi>He that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne throw the firſt ſtone at her;</hi> ſo let them raile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt women, who neuer tempted any woman to be bad: Yet this is an hard caſe. If a man raile againſt a woman, and know no lewdneſſe by any, he ſhall proue himſelfe a compound foole. If he rayle at woman, who in his owne experienced tryall had made many bad, he ſhall ſhew himſelfe a decompounded K. I doe not meane Knight: The beſt way is, he that knoweth none bad, let him ſpeake well of all: he who hath made more bad then he euer intended to make good, let him hold his peace leaſt hee ſhame himſelfe. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eſter Sowrenam.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11435:5"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVERE TO THE FIRST CHAPTER OF THE <hi>Arraignment of Women.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Author of this <hi>Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> had performed his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe either anſwerable to the Title, or the Arguments of the Chapters; hee had beene ſo farre off from being anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by me, that I ſhould haue commended ſo good a labour, which is imployed to giue vice iuſt reproofe, and vertue honourable report. But at the very firſt entrance of his diſcourſe, in the very firſt page, he diſcouereth himſelfe neither to haue truth in his promiſe, nor religious performance. If in this anſwere I doe vſe more vehement ſpeeches then may ſeeme to correſpond the naturall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Woman; yet all iudicious Readers ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that I vſe more mildneſſe then the cauſe I haue in hand prouoketh me vnto.</p>
               <p>I am not onely prouoked by this Authour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend women, but I am more violently vrged to defend diuine Maieſtie, in the worke of his Creation. In
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11435:6"/>which reſpect I ſay with Saint <hi>Ierome,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Cipria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> Meam iniuriam patienter ſuſtinui, impietatem contra deum ferre non potui.</hi> For as Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Sup. Math.</note> 
                  <hi>iniurias Dei diſsimulare impium eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If either <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, or <hi>Lucian</hi> the Atheiſt ſhould vndertake the like worke, could the owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe to write more blaſphemouſly, or the other to ſcoffe and flout at the diuine Creation of Woman, more prophanely then this irreligious Author doth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Homer</hi> doth report in his Illiads, that there was at the ſiege of <hi>Troy,</hi> a Graecian, called <hi>Therſites,</hi> whoſe wit was ſo blockiſh, he was not worthy to ſpeake: yet his diſpoſition was ſo precipitate, hee could not hold his tongue <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> in all record of Hiſtories can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo likely paraleld as with this <hi>Therſites.</hi> What his compoſition of body is I know not, but for his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition otherwiſe, in this Pamphlet I know, he is as monſtrous as the worke is miſhapen, which ſhall plainely appeare in the examination of the firſt page onely.</p>
               <p>The Argument of the firſt Chapter is, <hi>to ſhew to what vſe Women were made;</hi> it alſo ſheweth, <hi>That moſt of them degenerate from the vſe they were framed vnto,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now, to ſhew to what vſe woman was made, hee beginneth thus. <hi>At the firſt beginning a Woman was made to bee an helper to Man: And ſo they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for they helpe to conſume and ſpend,</hi> &amp;c. This is all the vſe, and all the end which the Authour ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe in all his diſcourſe for the creation of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Marke a ridiculous ieaſt in this: Spending and conſuming of that which Man painfully getteth, is by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11435:6"/>this Authour the vſe for which Women were made. And yet (ſaith hee in the Argument) <hi>moſt of them degenerate from the vſe they were framed vnto.</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was made to ſpend and conſume at the firſt: But women doe degenerate from this vſe, <hi>Ergo, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſe</hi> doth contradict himſelfe. Beſide this egregious folly, he runneth into horrible blaſphemy. VVas the end of Gods creation in VVoman to ſpend and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume? Is <hi>helper</hi> to be taken in that ſence, to helpe to <hi>ſpend?</hi> &amp;c. Is ſpending and conſuming, <hi>helping?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He runneth on, and ſaith, <hi>They were made of a Rib, and that their froward and crooked nature doth declare, for a Rib is a crooked thing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>VVoman was made of a crooked rib, ſo ſhe is croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of conditions. <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> was made as from <hi>Adam</hi> of clay and duſt, ſo he is of a durty and muddy diſpoſition: The inferences are both alike in either; woman is no more crooked, in reſpect of the one; but he is blaſphemous in reſpect of the other. Did Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man receiue her ſoule and diſpoſition from the rib; Or as it is ſaid in <hi>Geneſis, God did breath in them the ſpirit of life?</hi> Admit that this Authors doctrine bee true, that woman receiueth her froward and crooked diſpoſition from the rib, Woman may then conclude vpon that Axiome in Philoſophy,
<note place="margin">To take a van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage vpon a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage.</note> 
                  <hi>Quicquid efficit ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, illud eſt magis tale,</hi> That which giueth quality to a thing, doth more abound in that quality; as fire which heateth, is it ſelfe more hot: The Sunne which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth light, is of it ſelfe more light: So, if Woman receaued her crookedneſſe from the rib, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from the Man, how doth man excell in crookedneſſe, who hath more of thoſe crooked ribs?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11435:7"/>See how this vaine, furious, and idle Authour furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth woman with an Argument againſt himſelfe, and others of his Sexe.</p>
               <p>The Authour hauing deſperately begunne, doth more raſhly and impudently runne on in blaſphemy, which he doth euidently ſhew in the inference vpon his former ſpeeches: And therefore (ſaith he) <hi>Euer ſince they haue beene a woe vnto Man, and follow the liue of the firſt leader.</hi> Now let the Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pleaſe to conſider how diſhoneſtly this Authour dealeth, who vndertaking a particular, proſecuteth and perſecuteth a generall, vnder the cloake and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of lewd, idle, and froward women, to rage and raile againſt all women in generall.</p>
               <p>Now, hauing examined what collections <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> hath wreſted out of Scriptures, to diſhonor and abuſe all women: I am reſolued, before I anſwere further particulars made by him againſt our ſexe, to collect and note out of Scriptures; Firſt, what incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and moſt excellent prerogatiues God hath beſtowed vpon women, in honour of them, and their Creation: Secondly, what choyſe God hath made of women, in vſing them as inſtruments to worke his moſt gracious and glorious deſignes, for the generall benefit of man-kind, both during the law of Nature, and of <hi>Moyſes:</hi> Thirdly, what excellent and diuine graces haue beene beſtowed vpon our Sexe, in the law of Grace, and the worke of Redemption: With a concluſion, that to manifeſt the worthineſſe of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they haue beene choſen to performe and publiſh the moſt happy and ioyfull benefits which euer came to man-kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11435:7"/>
               <head>CHAPTER II. <hi>What incomparable and excellent prerogatiues God hath beſtowed vpon Women, in their firſt Creation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this enſuing Chapter I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine briefly to obſerue (not curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcourſe at large) the ſinguler benefits and graces beſtowed vpon Women: In regard of which, it is firſt to bee conſidered; That the Almighty God in the worlds frame in his Diuine wiſedome, deſigned to himſelfe a maine end to which he ordayned all the workes of his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, in which hee being a moſt excellent worke-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, did ſo Create his workes, that euery ſucceeding worke was euer more excellent then what was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Created: hee wrought by degrees, prouiding in all for that which was and ſhould be the end.</p>
               <p>It appeareth by that Soueraignty which God gaue to <hi>Adam</hi> ouer all the Creatures of Sea and Land,
<note place="margin">The preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues giuen to women in their Creation.</note> that man was the end of Gods creation, wherevpon it doth neceſſarily, without all exception follow, that <hi>Adam,</hi> being the laſt worke, is therefore the moſt excellent worke of creation: yet <hi>Adam</hi> was not ſo abſolutely perfect, but that in the ſight of God, he wanted an <hi>Helper:</hi> Wherevpon God created the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man his laſt worke, as to ſupply and make abſolute that imperfect building which was vnperfected in man, as all Diuines do hold, till the happy creation of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11435:8"/>the woman. Now of what eſtimate that Creature is and ought to be,
<note place="margin">The laſt worke.</note> which is the laſt worke, vpon whom the Almighty ſet vp his laſt reſt: whom he made to to adde perfection. to the end of all creation I leaue rather to be acknowledged by others, then reſolued by my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>It is furthermore to be conſidered, as the Maide, <hi>in her Muſſell for Melaſtomus</hi> hath obſerued: that God intended to honour woman in a more excellent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<note place="margin">Created vpon a refined ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</note> in that he created her out of a ſubiect refined, as out of a Quintiſſence: For the ribbe is in Subſtance more ſolid, in place as moſt neare, ſo in eſtimate moſt deare, to mans heart, which doth preſage that as ſhe was made for an helper, ſo to be an helper to ſtay, to ſettle all ioy, all contents, all delights, to and in mans heart, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
               <p>That delight,
<note place="margin">A better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</note> ſolace, and pleaſure, which ſhall come to man by woman, is prognoſticated by that place wherein woman was created: for ſhe was framed in Paradice, a place of all delight and pleaſure, euery element hath his creatures, euery creature doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponde the temper and the inclination of that ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein it hath and tooke his firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <hi>eſſe,</hi> or being. So that woman neither can or may degenerate in her diſpoſition from that naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the place, in which ſhe was firſt framed, ſhe is a Paradician, that is, a delightfull creature, borne in ſo delightfull a country.</p>
               <p>When woman was created,
<note place="margin">Men are worldlings, Women para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicians.</note> God brought her vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> and then did ſolempniſe that moſt auſpicious Marriage betwixt them, with the greateſt Maieſtie, and magnificence that heauen, or earth might afford.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11435:8"/>God was the Father, which gaue ſo rich a iewell: God was the Prieſt which tied ſo inſeperable a knot.
<note place="margin">Womans mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> God was the Steward which prouided all the pleaſures, all the dainties, all the bleſſings, which his deuine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might affoord, in ſo delightfull a place.</p>
               <p>The woman was married to <hi>Adam,</hi> as with a moſt ſure and inſeparable band, ſo with a moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate and dutifull loue: <hi>Adam</hi> was enioyned to receaue his wife, as is noted in the Bible printed 1595.</p>
               <p>There is no loue (alwayes excepting the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue) which is ſo highly honoured, ſo graciouſly rewarded, ſo ſtraightly commanded, or which being broken, is ſo ſeuerely puniſhed, as the loue and duty which Children owe to their Parents: Yet this loue albeit neuer ſo reſpectiue, is diſpenſed withall in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that loue which a man is bound to beare to his wife: <hi>For this cauſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Adam,</hi> (as from the mouth of God) <hi>ſhall a man leaue Father and Mother, and cleaue onely to his Wife.</hi> This word <hi>cleaue</hi> is vttered in the Hebrew with a more ſignificant emphaſie, then any other Language may expreſſe; ſuch a cleauing and ioyning together, which admitteth no ſeperation. It may be neceſſarily obſerued, that that gift of the woman was moſt ſingularly excellent, which was to bee accepted and entertained with ſo ineſtimable a loue,
<note place="margin">The wedding Ring.</note> and made inſeparable by giuing and taking the Ring of Lone, which ſhould be endleſſe.</p>
               <p>Now, the woman taking view of the Garden, ſhee was aſſaulted with a Serpent of the maſculine gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; who maliciouſly enuying the happineſſe in which man was at this time, like a miſchieuous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11435:9"/>Politician,
<note place="margin">Womans temptation.</note> hee practiſed by ſupplanting of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to turne him out of all: For which end he moſt craftily and cunningly attempteth the woman; and telleth her, that therefore they were forbidden to eate of the fruit which grew in the middeſt of the Garden, that in eating, they ſhould not be like vnto God: Wherevpon the woman accepted, taſted, and gaue to her Husband. In accepting the Serpents of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, there was no ſinne; for there was no ſinne till the fruit was eaten: Now, albeit I haue vndertaken the defence of women, and may in that reſpect be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, in taking all aduantages I may, to defend my ſexe.</p>
               <p>There are many pregnant places in the Scripture which might be alleaged to extenuate the ſin of the Woman, in reſpect of the ſinne of <hi>Adam:</hi> it is ſaid <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 25. <hi>Sinne had his beginning in woman, Ergo,</hi> his fulneſſe in man.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>By one mans ſinne death came into the world,</hi> without mention of the woman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note> to whom he affirmeth, <hi>that all die in Adam,</hi> in which the fulneſſe and effects of ſinne are charged vpon <hi>Adam</hi> alone, not but that woman had her part in the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, but not in ſo high a degree as the man.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Adam</hi> had eaten,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adam</hi> his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences vpon his fall.</note> and ſinne was now in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hee beginneth to multiply ſinne vpon ſinne: firſt he flieth from the ſight of God; next, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to account, he excuſeth his ſinne; and doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate (as it were) with Almightie God, and tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him, <hi>That woman which thou gaueſt mee, gaue me, and I did eate:</hi> As who ſhould ſay, if thou hadſt not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11435:9"/>giuen the cauſe, I had not beene guilty of the effect; making (heerein) God the Authour of his fall.</p>
               <p>Now what is become of that loue,
<note place="margin">Adams loue like his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens in theſe dayes.</note> which <hi>Adam</hi> was bound to beare towards his wife? He chargeth her with all the burden; ſo he may diſcharge himſelfe he careth little how hee clog her.</p>
               <p>God hauing examined the offendors, and haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard the vttermoſt they could alledge for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, he pronounceth ſentence of death vpon them,
<note place="margin">Adam puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with iuſtice.</note> as a puniſhment in iuſtice due and deſerued. Iuſtice he adminiſtred to <hi>Adam:</hi> Albeit the woman doth taſte of iuſtice, yet mercy is reſerued for her, and of all the workes of mercy which mankinde may hope for, the greateſt, the moſt bleſſed,
<note place="margin">Woman puniſhed by Iuſtice, relieued by Mercy.</note> and the moſt ioyfull is promiſed to woman.</p>
               <p>Woman ſupplanted by taſting of fruit, ſhe is puniſhed in bringing forth her owne fruit. Yet what by fruit ſhe loſt, by fruit ſhe ſhall recouer.</p>
               <p>What more gratious a gift could the Almightie promiſe to woman,
<note place="margin">The incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of womens wits.</note> then to bring forth the fruit in which all nations ſhall be bleſſed? ſo that as wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was a meanes to looſe Paradice, ſhe is by this, made a meanes to recouer Heauen. <hi>Adam</hi> could not vpbraid her for ſo great a loſſe, but he was to honour her more for a greater recouery: all the puniſhments inflicted vpon women, are encountred with moſt gratious bleſſings &amp; benefits; ſhe hath not ſo great cauſe of dolour in one reſpect, as ſhee hath infinite cauſe of ioy in another. She is commanded to obey her huſband; the cauſe is, the more to encreaſe her glorie. Obedience is better then Sacrifice:
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1:</note> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more acceptable before God then to obey:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11435:10"/>women are much bound to God, to haue ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a vertue enioyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them for their pennance.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the curſes and puniſhments heaped vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Serpent, what greater ioy could ſhe heare, or what greater honour could be done vnto her, then to heare from the voyce of God theſe words; <hi>I will put cumitie betwixt the woman and thee, betwixt thy ſeede and her ſeede,</hi> and that her ſeed ſhould breake the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head? This muſt perforce be an exceeding ioy for the woman, to heare and to be aſſured that her fruit ſhould reuenge her wrong.</p>
               <p>After the fall, and after they were all arraigned and cenſured, and that now <hi>Adam</hi> ſaw his wiues dowrie, and what bleſſings God hath beſtowed vpon her,
<note place="margin">Womans name anſwerable to her nature.</note> hee being now a bondſlaue to death and hell, ſtroke dead in regard of himſelfe, yet hee comforts himſelfe, he taketh heart from grace, he engageth his hope vpon that promiſe which was made to the woman. Out of this moſt comfortable and bleſſed hope hee now calleth his wife by a name, in whoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects not onely he, but all mankinde ſhould moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly ſhare: hee calleth her <hi>Eue,</hi> which is, the mother of the liuing: which is ſutable as well in reſpect of the promiſe made to her and her ſeede, as in reſpect of thoſe imployments for which in her creation ſhe and all women are deſigned, to be helpers, comforters, Ioyes, and delights, and in true vſe and gouerment they euer haue beene and euer will be, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewed, maugre the ſhamefull, blaſphemous and prophane ſpeach of <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam,</hi> page 31. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining line 15. as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God had not made them onely to be a plague to a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11435:10"/>man, hee would neuer haue called them neceſſary euils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of what Scripture, out of what record, can hee proue theſe impious and impudent ſpeeches? They are onely faigned and framed out of his owne idle, giddie, furious, and franticke imaginations. If he had cited <hi>Euripides</hi> for his Author, hee had had ſome colour, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prophane Poet in <hi>Medea,</hi> vſeth theſe ſpeeches, <hi>Quod ſi Deorum aliquis mulierem for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mauit, opificem ſe malorum ſciat, maximum &amp; hominibus inimicum.</hi> If any of the Gods framed woman, let him know he was the worker of that which is naught, and what is moſt hurtfull to men. Thus a Pagan writeth prophanely, but for a Chriſtian to ſay, that God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth women <hi>neceſſary euils,</hi> is moſt intolerable and ſhamefull to be written and publiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>What choiſe God hath made of women to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to deriue his benefits to Mankinde.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Braham</hi> being in danger,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 20.</note> was bleſſed and preſerued in reſpect of <hi>Sara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi> by Gods prouidence was the means to bring the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Iſaac</hi> to fall vpon <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 27.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Aegyptian Mid-wiues were a meanes to preſerue the male children of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the murther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by <hi>Pharao.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:11435:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was preſerued by the daughter of <hi>Pharao.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Meſſengers ſent by Duke <hi>Ioſuab</hi> to view the Land of Promiſe,
<note place="margin">Ioſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2.6.</note> were harboured and freed from danger by a woman.</p>
               <p>When the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> had beene twentie yeres oppreſſed by <hi>Iabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan,
<note place="margin">Iudges 4.</note> Debbora</hi> and <hi>Iahell,</hi> two women; the one w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e the battell, the other ſlew the Generall.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Abimilech</hi> had murthered ſeauenty of his Brethren,
<note place="margin">Iudges 9.</note> he was puniſhed and ſlaine by a woman at the ſiege of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Micholl</hi> aduentured the hazard of her Fathers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to preſerue her Husband <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abigail</hi> by incomparable wiſedome with held <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> from ſhedding of innocent bloud.
<note place="margin">1 Kings 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Citie of <hi>Abdela</hi> being in danger,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 20.</note> was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by a wiſe woman of that Citie.</p>
               <p>In the great famine of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 Kings 17.</note> the widow of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta</hi> was choſen to preſerue <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue her.</p>
               <p>The like prouiſion did the woman,
<note place="margin">4 Kings 4.</note> a <hi>Sunamite,</hi> make for <hi>Elizeus,</hi> and <hi>Elizeus</hi> for the woman.</p>
               <p>When the bloud-Royall of <hi>Iudah</hi> had beene all murthered,
<note place="margin">4 Kings 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioas</hi> afterwards King, was preſerued by a woman.</p>
               <p>What was that noble aduenture ſo bleſſedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by <hi>Iudith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith.</note> in cutting off the head of <hi>Holofer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what wiſedome did Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> preſerue her people,
<note place="margin">Heſter.</note> and cauſed their enemies to be hanged?</p>
               <p>What a chaſt mirrour was <hi>Suſanna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suſanna.</note> who rather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded her life, then offend againſt God?</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11435:11"/>
               <p>Neuer was greater magnanimity ſhewed by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<note place="margin">2 Mach. 7.</note> then by that Mother which ſaw her ſeauen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren tormented moſt cruelly, yet ſhe encouraged them to the death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>What excellent bleſsings and graces haue beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon women in the Lawe of Grace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt which commeth in this place to be mentioned, is that bleſſed mother and mirrour of al woman-hood, the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> who was magnified in the birth of Ieſus, glorified by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, choſen by the Almighty to beare in her wombe the Sauiour of mankinde.</p>
               <p>With what a faithfull ſalutation did <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> Mother, entertaine the Virgin vpon her repaire vnto her?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anna</hi> the old Propheteſſe did miraculouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate our Sauiour.
<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The woman which had the iſſue of bloud:
<note place="margin">Math. 917.</note> the woman of <hi>Canaan, Ioh.</hi> 4. The <hi>Samaritan</hi> woman. <hi>Martha,</hi> the 11. of <hi>Iohn:</hi> all theſe and ſundry others are ſaued, healed, and haue their ſinnes forgiuen, in reſpect of their true and liuely faith.</p>
               <p>VVhat faith? what zeale? what deuotion did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11435:12"/>
                  <hi>Marie Magdelen</hi> ſhew toward Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.</note> in proſtrating her ſelfe at the feete of Ieſus, annoynting them with pretious oyntment, waſhing them with teares, and drying them with the haire of her head?</p>
               <p>With what bountie and deuotion did the <hi>Maryes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 8.</note> the wife of <hi>Herods</hi> ſteward, did <hi>Ioanna,</hi> with other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men contribute of their goods to Ieſus?</p>
               <p>How charitable was that poore widdow,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.2.</note> whoſe two Mites our Sauiour valued at a greater eſtimate, then any gift of any other whatſoeuer?</p>
               <p>In all dangers,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.3.</note> troubles, and extremities, which fell to our Sauiour, when all men fled from him, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or dead, women neuer forſooke him.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be ouer-tedious to repeate euery example of moſt zealous, faithfull, and deuout women, which I might in the new Teſtament, whoſe faith and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion was cenſured by our Sauiour to be without compare.</p>
               <p>I will conclude for women that they haue beene choſen both to ſet out Gods glory, and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of all mankinde, in more glorious and gratious imployments then men haue beene.</p>
               <p>The firſt promiſe of a Meſſias to come was made to a woman: the birth and bearing of that promiſed Meſſias was performed by a woman.</p>
               <p>The triumphant reſurrection with the conqueſt ouer death and hell, was firſt publiſhed and proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a woman.</p>
               <p>I might herevnto adde thoſe wiues, widdowes, and virgins, which flouriſhed in the primatiue Church, and all ſucceeding ages ſithence, who in all vertues haue excelled, and honoured both their ſexeen gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11435:12"/>and themſelues in particular, who in thier mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdomes, in their confeſſion of Ieſus, and in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and deuine vertues, haue in no reſpect beene inferiour vnto men.</p>
               <p>THus out of the ſecond and third Chapters of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> and out of the Old and New Teſtaments,
<note place="margin">The ſummon of womans bleſſings and graces.</note> I haue obſerued in proofe of the worthineſſe of our Sexe: Firſt, that woman was the laſt worke of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, I dare not ſay the beſt: She was created out of the choſen and beſt refined ſubſtance: She was created in a more worthy country: She was married by a moſt holy Prieſt: She was giuen by a moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Father: Her huſband was enioyned to a moſt inſeparable and affectionate care ouer her: The firſt promiſe of ſaluation was made to a woman: There is inſeperable hatred and enmitie put betwixt the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the Serpent: Her firſt name, <hi>Eua,</hi> doth preſage the nature and diſpoſition of all women, not onely in reſpect of their bearing, but further, for the life and delight of heart and ſoule to all mankinde.</p>
               <p>I haue further ſhewed the moſt gratious, bleſſed, and rareſt benefits, in all reſpects, beſtowed vpon women; all plainely and directly out of Scriptures.</p>
               <p>All which doth demonſtrate the blaſphemous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie of the authour of the <hi>Arraignement,</hi> who would or durſt write ſo baſely and ſhamefully, in ſo generall a manner, againſt our ſo worthy and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a ſexe.</p>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11435:13"/>
                  <head>To the courteous and friendly READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle <hi>READER,</hi> in my firſt Part I haue (what I might) ſtrictly obſerued a religious regard, not to entermingle any thing vnfitting the grauitie of ſo reſpectiue an Argument.</p>
                  <p>Now that I am come to this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Part, I am determined to ſolace my ſelfe with a little libertie: What aduantages I did forbeare to take in the former, I meane to make vſe of in this ſecond. <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> hath beene long vnanſwered, which had beene performed ſooner, if I had heard of his Booke before this laſt Terme: Or if the report of the Maidens anſwere had not ſtayed me. I haue not ſo amply and abſolutely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged my ſelfe in this Apologie as I would haue done, if either my leaſure had beene ſuch, as I could haue wiſhed, or the time more fauourable, that I might haue ſtayed. What my repaire into the Countrey enforceth me ſo leaue rather begunne then finiſhed; I meane (by Gods grace) to make perfect the next Terme: In the meane time (gentle <hi>READER)</hi> I bid thee kindly farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Eſter Sowrenam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11435:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>At what eſtimate Women were valued in ancient and former times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lato</hi> in his Bookes <hi>de Legibus,</hi> eſtimateth of Women, which doe equall Men in all reſpects, onely in bodie they are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but in wit and diſpoſition of minde nothing inferiour, if not ſuperiour. Wherevpon he doth in his ſo abſolute a Common-wealth, admit them to gouernment of Kingdomes and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, if they be either borne therevnto by Nature, or ſeated in gouernment by Election.</p>
               <p>It is apparent, that in the prime of antiquity, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were valued at higheſt eſtimate, in that all thoſe moſt ineſtimable and incomparable benefites which might either honour or preſerue Mankinde, are all generally attributed to the inuention of women, as may appeare in theſe few examples following.</p>
               <p>When <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> Mine and Thine,
<note place="margin">The incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens wit.</note> when right and wrong were decided by warres, and their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons then were the furniture of Nature, as Fiſts, Teeth, Stones, Stakes, or what came next to hand: A Ladie of an heroicall diſpoſition, called <hi>Bellona,</hi> did firſt inuent a more man-like and honourable weapon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11435:14"/>for warre, which was the ſword, with other Armour correſpondent, for which ſhe was at firſt (and ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince) honoured, as the Goddeſſe of warre.</p>
               <p>When at the firſt the fineſt Manchet and beſt bread in vſe was of Acorns, by the ſingular and practicall wit of a Lady called <hi>Ceres,</hi> the ſowing of Corne, and Tillage was inuented.</p>
               <p>The inuention of the ſeauen liberall Sciences, of all Arts, of all Learning, hath beene generally with one conſent aſcribed to the inuention of <hi>Iupiters</hi> daughters, the nine Muſes, whoſe Mother was a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Ladie <hi>Mneneoſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carmentis</hi> a Ladie, firſt inuented Letters, and the vſe of them by reading and writing.</p>
               <p>The royall and moſt delightfull exerciſe of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was firſt found out and practiſed by <hi>Diana,</hi> who thervpon is celebrated for the Goddeſſe of Hunting.</p>
               <p>The three Graces, which adde a <hi>decorum,</hi> and yeeld fauour to Perſons, Actions, and Speaches, are three Ladies, <hi>Aglaia, Thalia,</hi> and <hi>Enphroſune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The heroicall exerciſes of <hi>Olimpus,</hi> were firſt found and put in practiſe by <hi>Paleſtra</hi> a woman.</p>
               <p>The whole world being diuided into three parts in more ancient times, euery diuiſion to this day kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the name in honour of a woman.</p>
               <p>The foeminine Sexe is exceedingly honoured by Poets in their writings: They haue Gods as well for good things, as for bad; but they haue no women-Goddeſſes, but in things which are eſpecially good. They haue <hi>Bacchus</hi> for a drunken God, but no drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Goddeſſe. They haue <hi>Priapus</hi> the luſtfull God of Gardens, but no garden-Goddeſſes, except of late in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11435:14"/>the garden-Allies. They will obiect here vnto mee <hi>Venus,</hi> ſhe indeed is the Goddeſſe of Loue, but it is her blinde Sonne which is the God of Luſt; poore Ladie, ſhe hath but her ioynture in the Mannor of Loue, <hi>Cupid</hi> is Lord of all the reſt, hee hath the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; ſhe may not ſtrike a Deare, but ſhe muſt imploy her Sonne that ſawcie Boy.</p>
               <p>For Pride, they held it ſo farre from women, that they found out <hi>Nemeſis</hi> or <hi>Rhamnuſia,</hi> to puniſh and reuenge pride, but none to infect with pride.</p>
               <p>They haue <hi>Pluto</hi> the God of Hell, but no proper Goddes of hell; but <hi>Proſerpina,</hi> whom <hi>Pluto</hi> forcibly tooke from Mount <hi>Aetna,</hi> and carried her away, and made her Queene of Hell; yet ſhe doth not remaine in Hell but one halfe of the yeare, by a decree from <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I ſhould recite and ſet downe all the honourable records and Monuments for and of women, I might write more Bookes then I haue yet written lines. I will leaue and paſſe ouer the famous teſtimonies of forreine Kingdomes and Common-wealths, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Sexe: and I will onely mention ſome few examples of our owne Countrey and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which haue been incomparably benefited and honoured by women.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the olde Britaines, our firſt Anceſtors, the valiant <hi>Boadicea,</hi> that defended the liberty of her Countrey, againſt the ſtrength of the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they were at the greateſt, and made them feele that a woman could conquer them who had conquered almoſt all the men of the then known world.</p>
               <p>The deuout <hi>Helen,</hi> who beſides that, ſhe was the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11435:15"/>Mother of that religious and great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who firſt ſeated Chriſtian Religion in the Emperiall throne, &amp; in that reſpect may be ſtiled the mother of Religion, is ſtill more honoured for her ſingular pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and charitie towards him and his members, who dyed for vs vpon the Croſſe, then for her care and induſtry in finding out the wood of that Croſſe on which he dyed.</p>
               <p>In the time of the <hi>Danes,</hi> chaſte <hi>Aemma,</hi> whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency carried her naked feete ouer the fire-hot Plow ſhares vnfelt; with the <hi>Saxons</hi> Queene <hi>Elfgiue</hi> the holy widdow, and the Kings daughter <hi>Edith</hi> a Virgin Saint, both greater Conquerers then <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great, that men ſo much boaſt of, who could not conquere himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Since the <hi>Normans,</hi> the heroicall vertues of <hi>Elenor</hi> wife to <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, who when her Husband in the Holy Land was wounded with a poyſoned Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, of which ther was no hope of recouery from the Chyrurgions, ſhe ſuckt the poyſon into her own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to free him: together, curing that mortall wound, and making her owne fame immortall: ſo that I thinke this one act of hers may equall all the acts that her great Husband did in thoſe warres beſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip,</hi> wife to <hi>Edward</hi> the third, no leſſe to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for being the Mother of ſo many braue chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then of ſo many good deeds, which worthily got her the title of good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Margaret</hi> the wiſe, wife to <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt, who if her Husbands fortune, valour, and foreſight, had beene anſwerable to hers, had left the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> to their owne Sonne, and not to a ſtranger.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11435:15"/>
               <p>The other <hi>Margaret</hi> of <hi>Richmond,</hi> mother to <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth, from whoſe breſts he may ſeeme to haue deriued as well his vertues as his life, in reſpect of her heroicall prudence and pietie; whereof, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monuments, both the Vniuerſities are ſtill wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, it was by the bleſſed meanes of <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> wife to <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth, that the bloudy wars betwixt the houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the red Roſe and the white vnited, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It was by the meanes of the moſt renowmed Queene (the happy Mother of our dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) that the two Kingdomes once mortall foes, are now ſo bleſſedly conioyned.</p>
               <p>And that I may name no more (ſince in one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were comprized all the qualities and endowments that could make a perſon eminent) <hi>Elizabeth</hi> our late Soueraigne, not onely the glory of our Sexe, but a patterne for the beſt men to imitate, of whom I will ſay no more, but that while ſhe liued, ſhe was the mirrour of the world, ſo then knowne to be, and ſo ſtill remembred, and euer will be.</p>
               <p>Daily experience, and the common courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth tell vs that women were by men in thoſe times highly valued, and in worth by men themſelues preferred, and held better then themſelues,</p>
               <p>I will not ſay that women are better then men, but I will ſay, men are not ſo wiſe as I would wiſh them to be, to wooe vs in ſuch faſhion as they do, except they ſhould hold and account of vs as their betters.</p>
               <p>What trauaile? what charge? what ſtudie?
<note place="margin">Men ſue to Women.</note> doe not men vndertake to gaine our good-will, loue, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11435:16"/>liking? what vehement ſuits doe they make vnto vs? with what ſolemne vowes and proteſtations do they ſolicite vs? they write, they ſpeake, they ſend, to make knowne what entire affection they beare vnto vs, that they are ſo deepely engaged in loue, except we doe compaſſion them with our loue and fauour, they are men vtterly caſt away. One he will ſtarue himſelfe, another will hang, another drowne, another ſtab, another will exile himſelfe from kinred and country, except they may obtaine our loues: What? will they ſay that we are baſer then themſelues? then they wrong themſelues exeedingly, to prefer ſuch vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuits to creatures inferiour to themſelues: Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors doe euer in their ſuites confeſſe a more worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the perſons to whom they ſue.
<note place="margin">Suint is alwaies preferred to the better.</note> Theſe kind of ſuits are from Nature, which cannot deceiue them: Nature doth tell them what women are, and cuſtom doth approue what nature doth direct. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Omnia appetunt bonum,</hi> euery thing by nature doth ſeeke after that which is good. Nature then doth cary men with violence, to ſeeke and ſue after women: They will anſwere, and ſeeke to elude this <hi>Maxime</hi> with a diſtinction, that <hi>bonum</hi> is duplex, <hi>aut verum, aut apparens,</hi> that goodneſſe or the thing which is good, is either truely good, or but apparantly good; ſo they may ſay, women are but apparantly good. But the heathen Orator and the deuine philoſopher to, affirme, if we follow the true direction of nature we ſhall neuer be deceiued. Nature in her vehement motions is not deceiued with apparant ſhewes. It is naturall, they will ſay, for the Male to follow the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male; ſo it is as naturall, for the Female to be better
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11435:16"/>then the Male, as appeareth to be true in obſeruation of Hawkes: the Spar-hawke is of more eſteeme then the Muſket; the Goſhawke more excellent then the Terſell; ſo in Falcons, the females doe excell: The like men are bound to acknowledge women; the rather in reſpect of their owne credit and honour. To what obſequious duty and ſeruice doe men binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to obtaine a fauour from their deuoted Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, which if he may obtaine he thinketh himſelfe to be much honoured, &amp; puts in place of moſt noted view, that the world may take note: He weareth in his hat, or on his breſt, or vpon his arme, the Gloue,
<note place="margin">Womens ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours eſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as relicks.</note> the Scarfe, or Ring of his Miſtriſſe: If theſe were not relickes from Saintly creatures, men would not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſo much deuotion vnto them.</p>
               <p>Amongſt diuers cauſes which proceede from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and cuſtome, why men are ſo earneſt Sutors to women, I haue obſerued one, which by practiſe is daily confeſſed. <hi>Plato</hi> ſayth, that Honeſtie is of that worthineſſe, that men are greatly enflamed with the loue of it; and as they doe admire it, ſo they ſtudie how to obtaine it: it is apparant, yong men which are vnmarried, and called batchelers, they may haue a diſpoſition, or may ſerue an apprentiſhip to honeſty,
<note place="margin">Honeſtie comes by mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans dovvrie.</note> but they are neuer free-men, nor euer called honeſt men, till they be married: for that is the portion which they get by their wiues. When they are once married, they are forthwith placed in the ranke of honeſt men, If queſtion be aſked, what is ſuch a man? it is preſently reſolued, he is an honeſt man: And the reaſon preſently added, for hee hath a wife; ſhee is the ſure ſigne and ſeale of honeſtie. It is vſuall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11435:17"/>amongſt old and graue fathers, if they haue a ſonne giuen to ſpending and companie-keeping, who is of a wild and riotous diſpoſition, ſuch a father ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be counſelled, helpe your ſonne to a good wife, marry him, marry him, that is the onely way to bring him to good order, to tame him, to bring him to be an honeſt man: The auncient fathers doe herein acknowledge a greater worthineſſe in women then in men; the hope which they haue of an vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſonne, to reclaime him, is all engaged vpon the woman.</p>
               <p>In no one thing, men doe acknowledge a more excellent perfection in women then in the eſtimate of the offences which a woman doth commit: the worthineſſe of the perſon doth make the ſinne more markeable.
<note place="margin">Womens faults more markable becauſe they are the better.</note> What an hatefull thing is it to ſee a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ouercome with drinke, when as in men it is noted for a ſigne of goodfellowſhip? and whoſoeuer doth obſerue it, for one woman which doth make a cuſtome of drunkenneſſe, you ſhall finde an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men: it is abhorred in women, and therefore they auoyd it: it is laughed at and made but as a ieſt amongſt men, and therefore ſo many doe practiſe it: Likewiſe if a man abuſe a Maide &amp; get her with child, no matter is made of it, but as a trick of youth; but it is made ſo hainous an offence in the maide, that ſhe is diſparaged and vterly vndone by it. So in all offences thoſe which men commit, are made light and as nothing, ſlighted ouer; but thoſe which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe commit, thoſe are made grieuous and ſhamefull, and not without iuſt cauſe: for where God hath put hatred betwixt the woman and the ſerpent,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11435:17"/>it is a foule ſhame in a woman to carry fauour with the deuill, to ſtayne her womanhoode with any of his damnable qualities, that ſhe will ſhake hands where God hath planted hate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> in his Pamphlet aggrauateth the offences of women in the higheſt degree, not onely exceeding, but drawing men into all miſcheife. If I do grant, that woman degenerating from the true end of womanhood, prooue the greateſt offenders, yet in graunting that, I doe thereby proue that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their creation are the moſt excellent creatures: for corruption, <hi>boni peſsima,</hi> the beſt thing corrupted proueth the worſt, as for example, the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous creature in heauen is by his fall the moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned deuill in hell: all the Elements in their puritie are moſt pretious, in their infection and abuſe moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: ſo the like in women, in their moſt exellent puritie of nature, what creature more gratious! but in their fall from God, and all goodneſſe, what crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more miſchieuous? which the deuill knowing he doth more aſſault woman then man, becauſe his gaine is greater, by the fall of one woman, then of twentie men. Let there be a faire maide, wife, or woman, in Countrie, towne or Citie,
<note place="margin">The deuill doth more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently tempt women then men. He is ſure of them when he will.</note> ſhe ſhall want no reſort of Serpents, nor any varietie of tempter: let there be in like ſort, a beautifull or perſonable man, he may ſit long enough before a woman will ſolicite him. For where the deuill hath good acquaintance, he is ſure of entertainement there, without reſiſtance: The Serpent at firſt tempted woman, he dare aſſault her no more in that ſhape, now he imployeth men to ſupply his part; and ſo they doe: for as the Serpent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11435:18"/>began with <hi>Eue</hi> to delight her taſte, ſo doe his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments draw to wine and banqueting; the next, the Serpent enticed her by pride, and tolde her ſhee ſhould be like to God; ſo doe his inſtruments; firſt, they will extoll her beauty, what a paragon ſhe is in their eyes;
<note place="margin">Diſſembling in men.</note> next, they will promiſe her ſuch mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as the beſt woman in the Pariſh or Country ſhall not haue better: What care they, if they make a thouſand oathes, and commit tenne thouſand periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo they may deceiue a woman? When they haue done all and gotten their purpoſe, then they diſcouer all the womans ſhame, and imploy ſuch an Author as this (to whoſe <hi>Arraignment</hi> I doe make haſte) to raile vpon her and the whole Sexe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:11435:18"/>
               <head>THE ARRAIGNMENT OF <hi>Joſeph Swetnam,</hi> who was the Author of the <hi>Arraignment of Women;</hi> And vnder his perſon, the arraignment <hi>of all idle, franticke, froward, and lewd men.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Oſeph Swetnam</hi> hauing written his raſh, idle, furious and ſhamefull diſcourſe againſt Women, it was at laſt deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into my hands, preſently I did acquaint ſome of our Sexe with the accident, with whom I did aduiſe what courſe wee ſhould take with him. It was concluded (that his vnworthineſſe being much like to that of <hi>Therſites,</hi> whom I haue formerly mentioned) wee would not anſwere him either with <hi>Achilles</hi> fiſt, or <hi>Stafford</hi>-law; neither plucke him in pieces as the <hi>Thracian</hi> woman did <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> for his intemperate rayling againſt women: But as he had arraigned women at the barre of fame and report; wee reſolued at the ſame barre where he did vs the wrong, to arraigne him, that thereby
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11435:19"/>we might defend our aſſured right: And withall (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting our ſelues) we reſolued to fauour him ſo far in his triall that the world might take notice there was no partiall or indirect dealing, but that he had as much fauour as he could defire, and farre more then he did or could deſerue.</p>
               <p>So that wee brought him before two Iudgeſſes,
<note place="margin">The Iudgeſſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Experience,</hi> who being both in place, no man can ſuſpect them with any indirect proceedings: For albeit, <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it ſelfe may be blinded by paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet when ſhe is ioyned with <hi>Experience,</hi> ſhee is knowne to be abſolute, and without compare. As for <hi>Experience,</hi> ſhe is knowne of her ſelfe to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable excellent in her courſes, ſhe knoweth how to vſe euery man in her practiſe; ſhe will whip the foole to learne him more wit; ſhe will puniſh the knaue to practiſe more honeſty; ſhe will curbe in the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and teach him to be warie; ſhe will trip vp the heeles of ſuch as are raſh and giddy, and bid them hereafter looke before they leape. To be ſhort, there is not in all the world, for all eſtates, degrees, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and conditions of men, ſo ſingular a Miſtreſſe, or ſo fit to be a Iudgeſſe as ſhe, onely one property ſhe hath aboue all the reſt, no man commeth before her but ſhe maketh him aſhamed, and ſhee will call and proue almoſt euery man a foole, eſpecially ſuch who are wiſe in their owne conceits.</p>
               <p>For his Iurie,
<note place="margin">The Iurie.</note> albeit we knew them to be of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and neareſt inward familiar friends, in whoſe company he was euer, and did ſpend vpon them all that he cou'd get, or deuiſe to get; yet wee did chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge no one of them, but were well pleaſed that his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11435:19"/>fiue Senſes, and the ſeauen deadly ſinnes ſhould ſtand for his Iury.</p>
               <p>The partie which did giue euidence againſt him,
<note place="margin">The Euidence.</note> we knew to bee a ſure Card, and one which would not faile in proofe of any thing, and ſuch proofe which ſhould be without all exception, <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a ſure witneſſe.</p>
               <p>So all things being accordingly prouided, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner was brought to the barre, where he was called and bid hold vp his hand, which hee did, but a falſe hand God he knowes, his enditement was red, which was this which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Joſeph Swetnam</hi> his Enditement.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Oſeph Swetnam,</hi> thou art endited by the name of <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> of <hi>Bedlemmore,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolie</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pamphlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker.</note>: For that thou the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the yeare &amp;c. Diddeſt moſt wickedly,
<note place="margin">An Endite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly, falſly, and ſcandalouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſh a lewd Pamphlet, entituled the <hi>Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Women;</hi> In which, albeit thou diddeſt honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretend to arraigne lewd, idle, froward and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant women, yet contrary to thy pretended pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thou diddeſt raſhly, and malitiouſly raile and rage againſt all women, generally writing and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11435:20"/>moſt blaſphemouſly that women by their Creator were made for <hi>Helpers,</hi> for <hi>Helpers</hi> (thou fayeſt) <hi>to ſpend and conſume that which Man painefully getteth;</hi> furthermore, thou doſt write, <hi>That being made of a rib, which was crooked, they are therefore crooked and froward in conditions, and that Woman was no ſooner made, but her heart was ſet vpon miſchiefe;</hi> which thou doeſt deriue to all the Sexe generally, in theſe words, <hi>And therefore euer ſince they haue beene a woe vnto man, and follow the line of their firſt leader.</hi> Further then all this, thou doeſt affirme an impudent lye vpon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, in ſaying, that God calleth them <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary euils, and that therefore they were created to bee a plague vnto man.</hi> Thou writeſt alſo, <hi>That women are prowde, laſciuous, froward, curſt, vnconſtant, idle, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſhameleſſe, and that they decke and dreſſe themſelues to tempt and allure men to lewdneſſe,</hi> with much and many more foule, intemperate, and ſcandalous ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> was asked what he ſaid to his enditement, <hi>Guilty, or not guiltie,</hi> hee pleaded the generall iſſue, <hi>not guiltie,</hi> being asked how hee would be tryed, he ſtood mute, for <hi>Conſcience</hi> did ſo confront him, that he knew vpon tryall there was no way but one; wherevpon hee thought it much better to put himſelfe vpon our mercy, then to hazard the tryall of his owne Iurie.</p>
               <p>Wherevpon we did conſider if we ſhould haue vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to be preſſed, the diſaduantage had beene ours: for then his fauourites would haue ſaid as ſome did ſay,
<note place="margin">Standeth mute.</note> that <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> did not ſtand mute, as miſdoubting the proofe of what he had written: But
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11435:20"/>ſeeing the Iudgeſſes, the Iurie, the Accuſer, and all others, moſt of them of the foeminine gender, he ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpelled the queſtion by vs, being made Generall, that they would rather condemne him to pleaſe a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, although in particular reſpect of himſelfe he knew they would fauour him. And beſides that hee held it a ſtrange courſe, that the ſelfe and the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould be Iudges and Accuſers, whereupon we reſolued to graunt him longer time to aduice with himſelfe whether he would put himſelfe to triall, or vpon better deliberation to recall his errours.</p>
               <p>But that the world might be ſatisfied in reſpect of the wrongs done vnto vs, and to maintaine our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable reputation, it was concluded, that my ſelfe ſhould deliuer before the Iudges, to all the aſſembly, ſpeaches to theſe effects following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The anſwere to all obiections which are materiall, made againſt Women.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable and Worſhipfull, and you of all degrees; it hath euer beene a common cuſtome amongſt Idle, and humerous Poets, Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Rimers, out of paſſionate diſcontents, or hauing little otherwiſe to imploy themſelues about, to write ſome bitter Satire-Pamphlet, or Rime, againſt women: in which argument he who could deniſe any thing more bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11435:21"/>or ſpitefully, againſt our ſexe, hath neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the liking, allowance, and applauſe of giddy headed people. Amongſt the rable of ſcurill writers, this priſoner now preſent hath acted his part, whom albeit women could more willingly let paſſe, then bring him to triall, and as euer heretofore, rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn ſuch authors the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deigne them any anſwere, yet ſeeing his booke ſo commonly bought vp, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a generall applauſe; we are therfore enforced to make anſwere in defence of our ſelues, who are by ſuch an author ſo extreamely wronged in publike view.</p>
               <p>You all ſee hee will not put himſelfe vpon triall: if we ſhould let it ſo paſſe, our ſilence might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plead vs for guiltie, ſo would his Pamphlet be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a greater currant and credite then formerly it hath beene: So that as well in reſpect of our ſexe, as for a generall ſatisfaction to the world, I will take this courſe with our priſoner, I will at this preſent examine all the obiections which are moſt materiall, which our aduerſarie hath vomited out againſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and not onely what he hath obiected, but what other authors of more import then <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> haue charged vpon women: alas, ſeely man he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth nothing but what he hath ſtolne out of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh writers, as <hi>Euphues,</hi> the <hi>Palace of Pleaſure,</hi> with the like, which are as eaſily anſwered as vaynly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. He neuer read the vehement and profeſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt our ſexe, as for <hi>Gracians, Euripides, Menan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Simonides, Sophocles,</hi> with the like, amongſt Latine writers <hi>Invenall, Plautus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But of all that euer I read, I did neuer obſerue ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11435:21"/>generall ſinceritie in any, as in this aduerſarie, which you ſhall finde I will make as manifeſt as the Sunne to ſhine at mid-day.</p>
               <p>It is the maine end that our aduerſarie aimeth at in all his diſcourſe, to proue and ſay that women are bad; if he ſhould offer this vpon particulers, no one would denie it: but to lauiſh generally againſt all women, who can endure it? You might <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Swetnam,</hi> with ſome ſhew of honeſtie haue ſayd, ſome women are bad, both by cuſtome and company, but you cannot avoide the brand, both of blaſphemie and diſhoneſtie, to ſay of women generally they are all naught, both in their creation and by nature, and to ground your inferences vpon Scriptures.</p>
               <p>I let paſſe your obiections in your firſt page; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are formerly anſwered, onely whereas you ſay, <hi>woman was no ſooner made, but her heart was ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on miſchiefe:</hi> if you had then ſaid, ſhe had no ſooner eaten of the fruit, but her heart was ſet vpon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, you had had ſome colour for your ſpeaches; not in reſpect of the womans diſpoſition, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration both of her firſt Tutor and her ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor: For whereas ſcripture doth ſay,
<note place="margin">The Deuill tooke the ſhape of man.</note> 
                  <hi>Woman was ſupplanted by a Serpent, Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> doth ſay, <hi>ſhe was ſupplanted by the deuill, which appeared to her in the ſhape of a beautifull yong man.</hi> Men are much beholding to this author, who will ſeeme to inſinuate, that the deuill would in ſo friendly and familier a manner, put on the ſhape of man, when he firſt began to practiſe miſchiefe: The deuill might make bold of them, whom he knew in time would proue his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11435:22"/>friends. Herevpon it may be imagined it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that Painters, and Picture-makers, when they would repreſent the deuill, they ſet him out in the deformed ſhape of a man; becauſe vnder that ſhape he began firſt to act the part of a diuell: and I doubt he neuer changed his ſuite ſithence. Here it is to be obſerued, that which is worſt is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the ſhape of a man; but what is the moſt glorious creature is repreſented in the beautie of a woman,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erpent gaue the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man bad coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and her husband bad example.</note> as Angels. Woman at the firſt might eaſily learne miſchiefe, where or how ſhould ſhe learne goodnes? her firſt Schoole-maſter was aboundant in miſchiefe, and her firſt huſband did exceede in bad examples. Firſt, by his example he taught her how to flye from God: next how to excuſe her ſinne: then how to cample and conteſt with God, and to ſay as <hi>Adam</hi> did, thou art the cauſe, for, the woman whom thou gaueſt me, was the cauſe I did eate. What <hi>Adam</hi> did at the firſt, bad huſbands practiſe with their wiues euer ſithence, I meane in bad examples. It was no good example in <hi>Adam,</hi> who hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his wife from the gift of God, and bound to her in ſo inſeperable a bond of loue, that forthwith he being taken tardie would preſently accuſe his wife &amp; put her in all the danger; but the woman was more bound to an vpright iudge, then to a louing huſband: it would not ſerue <hi>Adams</hi> turne, to charge her, therby to free himſelfe:
<note place="margin">Men doe ſhew themſelues the children of <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </note> It was an hard and ſtrange courſe, that he who ſhould haue beene her defender, is now become her greateſt accuſer. I may heare ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, by one mans ſinne, death,</hi> &amp;c. ſo by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11435:22"/>of originall ſinne in <hi>Adam,</hi> all men are infected with his diſeaſes; and looke what examples he gaue his wife at the firſt, the like examples and practiſes doe all men ſhew to women euer ſithence. Let mee ſpeake freely, for I will ſpeake nothing but truly, neither ſhall my words exceede my proofe.</p>
               <p>In your firſt and ſecond Page, you alledge <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> for exclaiming bitterly againſt women: And that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Women (like as Wine) doe make men drunke with their deuices.</hi> What of all this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam,</hi> a man which hath reaſon, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer obiect that vnto his aduerſary, which when it commeth to examination will diſaduantage himſelfe. Your meaning is, in the diſgrace of women to exalt men: but is this any commendation to men, that they haue been and are ouer-reacht by women? Can you glory of their holineſſe, whom by women proue ſinfull? or in their wiſedome,
<note place="margin">Fooliſh men tempted with outward ſheves.</note> whom women make fooles? or in their ſtrength, whom women ouercome? can you excuſe that fall which is giuen by the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker? or colour that foyle which is taken from wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Is holineſſe, wiſedome, and ſtrength, ſo ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeated in your Maſculine gender, as to be ſtained, blemiſhed, and ſubdued by women? But now I pray you let vs examine how theſe vertues in men ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, came by women to be ſo impotent. Doe you meane in comparatiue degree, that women are more holy, more wiſe, more ſtrong, then men? if you ſhould graunt this, you had ſmall cauſe to write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. But you will not admit this: What is, or are the cauſes then why men are ſo ouertaken by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11435:23"/>women? You ſet downe the cauſes in your fourth Page; there you ſay, <hi>They are dangerous for men to deale withall, for their faces are Lures, their beauties baytes, their lookes are nets, and their words are charmes,</hi> and all to bring men to ruine: <hi>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vitare Charibdim,</hi> whil'ſt he ſeeketh to auoide one miſchiefe, he falleth into another. It were more credit for men to yeeld our ſexe to be more holy, wiſe, and ſtrong, then to excuſe themſelues by the reaſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged: for by this men are proued to haue as litle wit as they are charged to exceed in wickedneſſe. Are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal &amp; dumbe ſhews ſuch potent baites, nets, lures, charmes, to bring men to ruine? Why? wilde Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, dotterels, and woodcockes, are not ſo eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled and taken? are men ſo idle, vaine, and weake, as you ſeeme to make them? Let mee now ſee how you can free theſe men from diſhoneſt mindes, who are ouertaken thus with beautie, &amp;c. How can beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiehurt?
<note place="margin">If men be hurt thanke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> how can it be a cauſe of a mans ruine, of it ſelfe? what, do women forcibly draw? why, men are more ſtrong? are they ſo eloquent to perſwade? why, men are too wiſe; are they miſchieuous to entiſe? men are more holy; how then are women cauſes to bring men to ruine? direct cauſes they cannot be in any reſpect; if they be cauſes, they are but accident all cauſes: A cauſe as Philoſophers ſay, <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non:</hi> a remote cauſe, which cauſe is ſeldome alleaged for cauſe, but where want of wit would ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and a guilty conſcience would excuſe it ſelfe by ſomething. Philoſophers ſay, <hi>Nemo leditur niſi a ſeipſo,</hi> no man is hurt but the cauſe is in himſelfe. The
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11435:23"/>prodigall perſon amongſt the <hi>Gracians</hi> is called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotes,</hi> as a deſtroyer, an vndoer of himſelfe: When an heart fraughted with ſinne doth prodigally lauiſh out a laſciuious looke out of a wanton eye; when it doth ſurfeit vpon the fight, who is <hi>Aſotos?</hi> who is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his laſciuious diſeaſe but himſelfe? <hi>Volenti non fit iniuria,</hi> hee who is wounded with his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, hath ſmall cauſe to complaine of anothers wrong: Might not a man as eaſily, and more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, when hee ſeeth a faire woman, which doth make the beſt vſe that ſhe can to ſet out her beautie, rather glorifie God in ſo beautifull a worke, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his ſoule with ſo laſciuious a thought? And for the woman, who hauing a Iewell giuen her from ſo deare a friend, is ſhe not to be commended rather that in the eſtimate which ſhe ſheweth, ſhee will as carefully and as curiouſly as ſhe may ſet out what ſhe hath receiued from Almighty God, then to be cenſured that ſhe doth it to allure wanton and laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious lookes? The difference is in the minds, things which are called <hi>Adiaphora,</hi> things indifferent, whoſe qualities haue their name from the vſes, are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo cenſured, and ſo vſed, as the minde is inclined which doth paſſe his verdict. A man and a woman talke in the fields together, an honeſt minde will ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of their talke anſwerable to his owne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas an euill diſpoſed minde will cenſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his lewd inclination.
<note place="margin">Womans beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is good, but the heart which doth ſurieit is naught.</note> When men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of beautie, and ſay, <hi>That womens dreſsings and attire are prouocations to wantonneſſe, and baites to allure men,</hi> It is a direct meanes to know of what diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11435:24"/>they are, it is a ſhame for men in cenſuring of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to condemne themſelues; but a common Inne cannot be without a common ſigne; it is a common ſigne to know a leacher, by complaining vpon the cauſe and occaſion of his ſurfeit; who had knowne his diſeaſe but by his owne complaint? It is extreme folly to complaine of another, when the roote of all reſteth within himſelfe; purge an infected heart, and turne away a lacinious eye, and then neither their dreffings, nor their beautie can any waies hurt you. Doe not men exceede in apparell, and therein ſet themſelues out to the view? Shall women betray themſelues and make it knowne that they are either ſo bad in their diſpoſition, or ſo wanton in their thoughts, or ſo weak in their gouernment as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that they are tempted and allured by men? Should women make themſelues more vaine then yongeſt children, to fall in loue with babyes. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſo farre off from being in any ſort prouoked to loue vpon the view of mens apparell,
<note place="margin">Women doe not fall in lone with men for their apparell.</note> and ſetting forth themſelues, that no one thing can more draw them from loue, then their vanitie in apparell. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men make difference betwixt colours and conditions, betwixt a faire ſhew, and a foule ſubſtance: It ſhewes a leuitie in man to furniſh himſelfe more with trim colours, then manlike qualities: beſides that, how can we lone at whom we laugh? We ſee him gallant it at the Court one day, &amp; braue it in the Country the next day; we ſee him weare that on his backe one week, which we heare is in the brokers ſhop the next: furthermore we ſee diuers weare apparell and colours
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11435:24"/>made of a Lordſhip, lined with Farmes and Granges, embrodered with all the plate, gold, and wealth, their Friends and Fathers left them: Are theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to loue or to laughter? Will or dare a woman truſt to their loue for one Moneth, who will turne her of the next? This is the ſurfeit which women take by braue apparell. They rather ſuſpect his worth, then wiſh his loue, who doth moſt exceede in braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. So M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Swetnam,</hi> doe you and all yours forbeare to cenſure of the dreſſings and attires of women for any ſuch lewd intent, as you imagine: Bad minds are diſcouered by bad thoughts and hearts. Doe not ſay and rayle at women to be the cauſe of mens ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, when the originall roote and cauſe is in your ſelues. If you bee ſo affected that you cannot looke but you muſt forthwith be infected, I doe maruaile <hi>(Ioſeph Swetnam)</hi> you ſet downe no remedies for that torment of Loue, as you call it: You bid men ſhunne and auoyde it, but thoſe be common and ordinary rules and inſtructions: yet not ſo ordinary, as able to reſtraine the extraordinary humors of your giddy company. I will do you and your friends a kindneſſe if you be ſo ſcorched with the flames of loue. <hi>Diogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> did long ſince diſcouer the ſoueraigne ſalue for ſuch a wound: The receipt is no great charge, your ſelfe may be the Apothecarie,
<note place="margin">A medicine for Loue. Tane. Hunger. A Halter.</note> it is comprehended in three words: Firſt, trie with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, next with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, if both theſe faile, the third is ſure, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This was <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> Antidote againſt that venemous infection. There are more milder remedies which you may put in practiſe: If your hearts be ſo fleſhly, or your eies
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11435:25"/>ſo tender that you dare truſt neither of them, then truſt to your reaſon to turne your eyes away, or truſt to your heeles as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did, to carrie all away.</p>
               <p>After you haue railed againſt women, you bring in a fable of a contempt betwixt the <hi>Winde</hi> and the <hi>Same;</hi> and you apply the morrall to women, when as it hath a farre other relation: for it euer hath been applyed to men, to inſtruct them in the gouernment of woman, for I pray you who is to gouerne, or who are to be gouerned? You ſhould ſeeme to come from the <hi>Sauromatians,</hi> whoſe wiues were their Maſters: but I will ſet you downe both the Fable and the Morrall, as it was written in Engliſh verſe long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>THe</hi> Sunne <hi>and</hi> Winde <hi>at variance did fall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe force was greateſt in the open field:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A trauailer they chuſe to deale withall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who makes him firſt vnto their force to yeeld</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To caſt off Cloake, they that agreement make,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The honour of the victory muſt take.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The</hi> Winde <hi>began and did encreaſe, each blaſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With raging beate vpon the ſilly man;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The more it blew, the more he graſped faſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And kept his Cloake, let</hi> Winde <hi>doe what it can?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When all in vaine the</hi> Winde <hi>his worſt had done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It ceaſt, and left a tryall to the</hi> Sunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The</hi> Sunne <hi>beginnes his beames for to diſplay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And by degrees in heate for to encreaſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:11435:25"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Trauailer then warme, doth make a ſtay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And by degrees his Cloake he doth releaſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At length is forc'd both Coate and Cloake to yeeld,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So giues the</hi> Sunne <hi>the honour of the field.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who by extreames doth ſeeke to worke his will,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By raging humors thinking ſo to gaine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May like the</hi> Winde <hi>augment his tempeſt ſtill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But at the length he findes his furie vaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For all he gets by playing franticke parts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He hard neth more the milde and gentle hearts.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like as all Plants, when at the firſt they ſpring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are tender, and ſoft bark'd on euery fide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But as they grow continuall ſtormes doe bring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thoſe are more hard which Northerne blaſts abide:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What's toward the Southerne tenderer we finde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And that more hard which feeles the Northern winde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nautre his courſe moſt carefully doth bend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From violence to ſeeke it ſelfe to arme;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where raging blaſts the trees would breake and rend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There Nature ſtriues to keepe her Plants from harme:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where violence is vnto Nature ſtrange,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Continuall cuſtome there doth Nature change.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So 't is with women, who by Nature milde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If they on froward crabbed Husbands light;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Continuall rage by cuſtome makes them wilde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For crooked natures alter gentle quite;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:11435:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men euermore ſhall this in triall finde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like to her vſage ſo is womans minde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As of themſelues, let men of others iudge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What man will yeeld to be compel'd by rage?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At crabbedneſſe and cruſtneſſe hearts doe grudge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And to reſist, themſelues they more engage:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forbeare the</hi> Winde, <hi>ſhine with the</hi> Sunne <hi>a while,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though ſhe be angry, ſhe will forthwith ſmile.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>This is the true application of the Morrall. As for that crookedneſſe and frowardneſſe with which you charge women, looke from whence they haue it; for of themſelues and their owne diſpoſition it doth not proceede, which is prooued directly by your owne teſtimonie:
<note place="margin">Woman of her ovvne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gentle, and milde.</note> for in your 46. Page, Line 15. You ſay, <hi>A young woman of tender yeares is flexible, obedient, and ſubiect to doe any thing, according to the will and pleaſure of her Husband.</hi> How commeth it then that this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and milde diſpoſition is afterwards altered? your ſelfe doth giue the true reaſon, for you giue a great charge not to marrie a widdow. But why? becauſe ſay you in the ſame Page, <hi>A widdow is framed to the conditions of another man.</hi> Why then, if a woman haue froward conditions, they be none of her owne, ſhe was framed to them. Is not our aduerſarie aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of himſelfe, to raile againſt women for thoſe faults which doe all come from men? Doth not hee moſt grieuouſly charge men to learne their wiues bad and corrupt behauiour?
<note place="margin">Men infect.</note> for hee ſaith plainely, <hi>Thou muſt vnlearne a widdow, and make her forget and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11435:26"/>forgoe her former corrupt &amp; diſordered behaniour.</hi> Thou muſt vnlearne her, <hi>Ergo,</hi> what fault ſhee hath, ſhee learned, her corruptnes commeth not from her own diſpoſition, but from her Huſbands deſtruction. Is it not a wonder, that your Pamphlets are ſo diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Are they not wiſe men to caſt away time and money vpon a Booke which cutteth their owne throates? 'Tis pittie but that men ſhould reward you for your writing; if it bee but as the Romane <hi>Sertorius</hi> did the idle Poet, hee gaue him a reward, but not for his writing, but becauſe he ſhould neuer write more; as for women, they laugh that men haue no more able a champion. This author commeth to baite women, or as hee fooliſhly ſayth, the <hi>Beare bayting, of Women,</hi> and he bringeth but a mungrell Curre, who doth his kinde, to braule and barke, but cannot bite. The milde and flexible diſpoſition of a woman is in philoſophy proued in the compoſition of her body, for it is a Maxime,
<note place="margin">The diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde doth anſwere the compoſition of the body.</note> 
                  <hi>Mores animi ſequntur temperaturam corporis,</hi> The diſpoſition of the minde is anſwerable to the temper of the body. A woman in the temperature of her body is tender, ſoft, and beautifull, ſo doth her diſpoſition in minde correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponde accordingly; ſhe is milde yeelding, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous; what diſpoſition accidentally happeneth vnto her, is by the contagion of a froward huſband, as <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam</hi> affirmeth.</p>
               <p>And experience proueth. It is a ſhame for a man to complaine of a froward woman, in many reſpects all concerning himſelfe. It is a ſhame he hath no more gouernment ouer the weaker veſſell. It is a ſhame he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11435:27"/>hath hardned her tender ſides, and gentle heart with his boiſtrous &amp; Northren blaſts.
<note place="margin">May men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vvithout cauſe?</note> It is a ſhame for a man to publiſh and proclaime houſhold ſecrets, which is a common practiſe amongſt men, eſpecially Drunkards, Leachers, and prodigall ſpend-thrifts: Theſe when they come home drunke, or are called in queſtion for their riotous miſdemeanours, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhew themſelues, the right children of <hi>Adam.</hi> They will excuſe themſelues by their wiues, and ſay that their vnquiteneſſe and frowardneſſe at home, is the cauſe that they runne abroad. An excuſe more fitter for a beaſt then a man. If thou wert a man thou wouldeſt take away the cauſe which vrgeth a woman to griefe and diſcontent, and not by thy frowardneſſe encreaſe her diſtemperature: forbeare thy drinking, thy luxurious riot, thy gaming, and ſpending, and thou ſhalt haue thy wife giue thee as little cauſe at home, as thou giueſt her great cauſe of diſquiet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Men which are men, if they chance to be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with froward wiues, either of their own making, or others marring, they would make a benefit of the diſcommodity, either try his skill to make her milde, or exerciſe his patience to endure her curſtneſſe: for all croſſes are inflicted either for puniſhment of finnes, or for exerciſe of vertues; but humorous men will ſooner marre a thouſand women, then out of an hundred make one good.</p>
               <p>And this ſhall appeare in the imputation which our aduerſarie chargeth vpon our ſexe,
<note place="margin">Men are the Serpents</note> to be laciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wanton and luſtfull: He ſayth, <hi>Women tempt, alure, and prouoke men.</hi> How rare a thing is it for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11435:27"/>women to proſtitute and offer themſelues? how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a practiſe is it for men to ſeeke and ſolicite wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to lewdneſſe? what charge doe they ſpare? what trauell doe they beſtow? what vowes, oathes and proteſtations doe they ſpend, to make them diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt? They hyer Pandors, they write letters, they ſeale them with damnations, and execrations, to aſſure them of loue, when the end proues but luſt: They know the flexible diſpoſition of Women and the ſooner to ouerreach them, ſome will pretend they are ſo plunged in loue that except they obtaine their deſire they will ſeeme to drown'd, hang, ſtab, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or baniſh themſelues from friends and countrie: What motiues are theſe to tender diſpoſitions? Some will pretend marriage, another offer continuall maintenance, but when they haue obtained their purpoſe, what ſhall a woman finde, iuſt that which is her euerlaſting ſhame and griefe, ſhee hath made her ſelfe the vnhappie ſubject to a luſtfull bodie; and the ſhamefull ſtall of a laſciuious tongue. Men may with foule ſhame charge women with this ſinne which they had neuer committed if ſhee had not truſted, nor had euer truſted if ſhee had not beene deceiued with vowes, oathes, and proteſtations. To bring a woman to offend in one ſinne, how many damnable ſinnes doe they commit? I appeale to their owne conſciences. The lewd diſpoſition of ſundry men doth appeare in this: If a woman or maide will yeeld vnto lewdneſſe, what ſhall they want? But if they would liue in honeſtie, what helpe ſhall they haue? How much will they make of the lewd? how
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11435:28"/>baſe account of the honeſt? how many pounds will they ſpend in bawdie houſes? but when will they beſtowe a penny vpon an honeſt maide or woman, except it be to corrupt them?</p>
               <p>Our aduerſary bringeth many examples of men which haue beene ouerthrowne by women.
<note place="margin">Shew a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans offence, but that man was the firſt beginner.</note> It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, before the fault is their owne. But I would haue him, or any one liuing, to ſhew any woman that offended in this ſinne of luſt, but that ſhe was firſt ſollicited by a man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helen</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Troyes</hi> burning; firſt, <hi>Paris</hi> did ſollicite her; next, how many knaues and fooles of the male kinde had <hi>Troy,</hi> which to maintaine whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would bring their Citie to confuſion.</p>
               <p>When you bring in examples of lewd women, and of men which haue beene ſtained by women, you ſhew your ſelfe both franticke, and a prophane irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious foole to mention <hi>Indith</hi> for cutting off <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferues</hi> head, in that rancke.</p>
               <p>You challenge women for vntamed and vnbride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led tongues; there was neuer woman was euer noted for ſo ſhameleſſe, ſo brutiſh, ſo beaſtly a ſcold as you proue your ſelfe in this baſe and odious Pamphlet: You blaſpheme God, you raile at his Creation, you abuſe and ſlander his Creatures; and what immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt or impudent ſcurilitie is it, which you doe not expreſſe in this lewd and lying Pamphlet?</p>
               <p>Hitherto I haue ſo anſwered all your obiections againſt Women, that as I haue not defended the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of any; ſo I haue ſet downe the true ſtate of the queſtion. As <hi>Eue</hi> did not offend without the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11435:28"/>temptation of a Serpent; ſo women doe ſeldome offend, but it is by prouocation of men. Let not your impudencie, nor your conforts diſhoneſtie, charge our ſexe hereafter, with thoſe ſinnes of which you your ſelues were the firſt procurers. I haue in my diſcourſe, touched you, and all yours, to the quick. I haue taxed you with bitter ſpeaches; you will (perhaps) ſay I am a rayling ſcold. In this obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Ioſeph Swetnam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A difference betwixt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering.</note> I will teach you both wit and honeſtie: The difference betwixt a railing ſcold, and and an honeſt accuſes, is this, the firſt rageth vpon paſſionate furie, without bringing cauſe or proofe; the other bringeth direct proofe for what ſhe alleag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: you charge women with clamorous words, and bring no proofe; I charge you with blaſphemie, with impudencie, ſcurilitie, foolery, and the like. I ſhew iuſt and direct proofe for what I ſay; it is not my deſire to ſpeake ſo much, it is your deſert to prouoke me vpon iuſt cauſe ſo farre; it is no railing to call a Crow blacke, or a Wolfe a rauenour, or a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard a beaſt; the report of the truth is neuer to be blamed, the deſeruer of ſuch a report, deſerueth the ſhame.</p>
               <p>Now, for this time, to draw to an end; let me aſke according to the queſtion of <hi>Caſsian, Cui bono?</hi> what haue you gotten by publiſhing your Pamphlet; good I know you can get none. You haue (perhaps) plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the humors of ſome giddy, idle conceited per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: But you haue died your ſelfe in the colours of ſhame, lying, ſlandering, blaſphemie, ignorance, and the like.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:11435:29"/>
               <p>The ſhortneſſe of time and the weight of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe call me away, and vrge me to leaue off thus abruptly, but aſſure your ſelfe where I leaue now, I will by Gods grace ſupply the next Terme, to your ſmall content. You haue exceeded in your furie againſt Widdowes, whoſe defence you ſhal heare of at the time aforeſaide, in the meane ſpace recollect your wits, write out of deliberation, not out of furie; write out of aduice, not out of idleneſſe; forbeare to charge women with faults which come from the contagion of Maſculine ſerpents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:11435:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A DEFENCE OF</hi> Women, <hi>againſt the Author of the</hi> Arraignment of Women.</head>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AN idle companion was raging of late,</l>
                  <l>Who in furie 'gainſt Women expreſſeth his hate:</l>
                  <l>Hee writeth a Booke, an <hi>Arraignment</hi> he calleth,</l>
                  <l>In which againſt women he curriſhly bawleth.</l>
                  <l>He deſerueth no anſwere but in Ballat or Ryme,</l>
                  <l>Vpon idle fantaſtickes who would caſt away time:</l>
                  <l>Any anſwere may ſerue an impudent lyar,</l>
                  <l>Any mangie ſcab'd horſe doth fit a ſcal'd Squire:</l>
                  <l>In the ruffe of his furie, for ſo himſelfe faith,</l>
                  <l>The blaſphemous companion he ſhamefully playeth.</l>
                  <l>The woman for an <hi>Helpler,</hi> God did make he doth ſay,</l>
                  <l>But to <hi>Helpe to conſume and ſpend all away.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus, at Gods creation to flout and to ieſt,</l>
                  <l>Who but an Atheiſt would ſo play the beaſt?</l>
                  <l>The Scriptures doe proue that when <hi>Adam</hi> did fall,</l>
                  <l>And to death and damnation was thereby a thrall.</l>
                  <l>Then woman was an <hi>Helper,</hi> for by her bleſſed ſeed,</l>
                  <l>From Hell and damnation all mankinde was freed.</l>
                  <l>He ſaith, women are froward, which the rib doth declare,</l>
                  <l>For like as the Rib, ſo they crooked are:</l>
                  <l>The Rib was her Subiect for body we finde,</l>
                  <l>But from God came her Soule, and diſpoſe of her minde.</l>
                  <l>Let no man thinke much if women compare,</l>
                  <l>That in their creation they much better are:</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:11435:30"/>
                  <l>More bleſsings therein to women doe fall,</l>
                  <l>Then vnto mankinde haue beene giuen at all.</l>
                  <l>Women were the laſt worke, and therefore the beſt,</l>
                  <l>For what was the end, excelleth the reſt.</l>
                  <l>For womans more honour, it was ſo aſsign'd,</l>
                  <l>She was made of the rib of mettall refin'd:</l>
                  <l>The Countrey doth alſo the woman more grace,</l>
                  <l>For Paradice is farre the more excellent place.</l>
                  <l>Yet women are miſchienous, this Author doth ſay,</l>
                  <l>But Scriptures to that directly ſay nay:</l>
                  <l>God ſaid, <hi>'twixt the Woman and Serpent for euer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strong hatred he would put, to be qualified neuer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The woman being hatefull to the Serpents condition,</l>
                  <l>How excellent is ſhe in her diſpoſition?</l>
                  <l>The Serpent with men in their workes may agree,</l>
                  <l>But the Serpent with women that neuer may be.</l>
                  <l>If you aske how it happens ſome women proue naught,</l>
                  <l>By men turn'd to Serpents they are ouer-wrought.</l>
                  <l>What the Serpent began, men follow that ſtill,</l>
                  <l>They tempt what they may to make women doe ill.</l>
                  <l>They will tempt, and prouoke, and follow vs long:</l>
                  <l>They deceiue vs with aithes, and a flattering tongue.</l>
                  <l>To make a poore Maiden or woman a whore,</l>
                  <l>They care not how much they ſpend of their ſtore.</l>
                  <l>But where is there a man that will any thing giue</l>
                  <l>That woman or maide may with honeſtie liue?</l>
                  <l>If they yeeld to lewd counſell they nothing ſhall want,</l>
                  <l>But for to be honeſt, then all things are ſcant.</l>
                  <l>It proues a bad nature in men doth remaine.</l>
                  <l>To make women lewd their purſes they ſtraine.</l>
                  <l>For a woman that's honeſt they care not a whit,</l>
                  <l>Theyle ſay ſhe is honeſt becauſe ſhe lackes wit.</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:11435:30"/>
                  <l>Theyle call women whores, but their ſtakes they might ſaue,</l>
                  <l>There can be no Whore, but there muſt be a Knaue.</l>
                  <l>They ſay that our dreſsings, and that our attire</l>
                  <l>Are cauſes to moue them to luſtfull fire.</l>
                  <l>Of all things which are we euermore finde,</l>
                  <l>Such thoughts doe ariſe as are like to the minde.</l>
                  <l>Mens thoughts being wicked they wracke on vs thus,</l>
                  <l>That ſcandall is taken, not giuen by vs.</l>
                  <l>If their ſight be ſo weake, and their frailtie be ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Why doe they then gaze at our beauty ſo much?</l>
                  <l>Plucke away thoſe ill roots whence ſinne doth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Amend wicked thoughts, or plucke out the eyes.</l>
                  <l>The humors of men, ſee how froward they bee;</l>
                  <l>We know not to pleaſe them in any degree:</l>
                  <l>For if we goe plaine we are ſluts they doe ſay,</l>
                  <l>They doubt of our honeſty if we goe gay;</l>
                  <l>If we be honeſt and merrie, for giglots they take vs,</l>
                  <l>If modeſt and ſober, then proud they doe make vs:</l>
                  <l>Be we houſewifly quicke, then a ſhrew he doth keepe,</l>
                  <l>If patient and milde, then he ſcorneth a ſheepe.</l>
                  <l>What can we deuiſe to doe or to ſay,</l>
                  <l>But men doe wreſt all things the contrary way.</l>
                  <l>'Tis not ſo vncertaine to follow the winde,</l>
                  <l>As to ſeeke to pleaſe men of ſo humerous minde.</l>
                  <l>Their humors are giddy, and neuer long laſting,</l>
                  <l>We know not to pleaſe them, neither full nor yet faſting.</l>
                  <l>Either we doe too little, or they doe too much:</l>
                  <l>They ſtraine our poore wits, their humors are ſuch.</l>
                  <l>They ſay, women are proud wherein made they triall?</l>
                  <l>They moou'd ſome lewd ſuit, and had the deniall:</l>
                  <l>To be croſt in ſuch ſuites, men cannot abide,</l>
                  <l>And therevpon we are entitled with pride.</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:11435:31"/>
                  <l>They ſay we are curſt and froward by kinde,</l>
                  <l>Our mildneſſe is changed, where raging we finde,</l>
                  <l>A good <hi>Iacke</hi> ſaye; the prouerbe, doth make a good <hi>Gill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A curſt froward Husband doth change womans will.</l>
                  <l>They vſe vs (they ſay) as neceſſary euils,</l>
                  <l>We haue it from them, for they are our deuils.</l>
                  <l>When they are in their rages and humerous fits,</l>
                  <l>They put vs poore women halfe out of our wits.</l>
                  <l>Of all naughty women name one if you can,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe proued bad, it came by a man.</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Helen</hi> forſooke her Husband of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A man called <hi>Paris,</hi> betrayed that peece.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Medea</hi> did rage, and did ſhamefully murther,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>laſon</hi> was cauſe, which her miſchiefe did further.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Creſſide</hi> was falſe, and changed her loue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diomedes</hi> her heart by conſtraint did remoue.</l>
                  <l>In all like examples the world may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Where women proue bad, there men are not free.</l>
                  <l>But in thoſe offences they haue the moſt ſhare,</l>
                  <l>Women would be good, if Serpents would ſpare.</l>
                  <l>Let Women and Maides whatſoeuer they be,</l>
                  <l>Come follow my counſell, be warned by me.</l>
                  <l>Truſt not mens ſuites, their loue proueth luſt,</l>
                  <l>Both hearts, tongues, and pens, doe all proue vniuſt.</l>
                  <l>How faire they will ſpeake and write in their loue,</l>
                  <l>But put them to tryall how falſe doe they proue?</l>
                  <l>They loue hot at firſt, when the loue is a ſtranger,</l>
                  <l>But they will not be tied to racke and to manger.</l>
                  <l>What loue call you that when men are a wooing,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke nothing elſe but ſhame and vndoing.</l>
                  <l>As women in their faults I doe not commend,</l>
                  <l>So wiſh I all men their lewd ſuites they would end.</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:11435:31"/>
                  <l>Let women alone, and ſeeke not their ſhame,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall haue no cauſe then women to blame.</l>
                  <l>'Tis like that this Author againſt ſuch doth bawle.</l>
                  <l>Who by his temptations haue gotten a fall.</l>
                  <l>For he who of women ſo wickedly deemeth,</l>
                  <l>Hath made them diſhoneſt, it probably ſeemeth.</l>
                  <l>He hath beene a Traueller, it may be well ſo,</l>
                  <l>By his tales and reports as much we doe know.</l>
                  <l>He promiſeth more poyſon againſt women to thruſt,</l>
                  <l>He doth it for phiſicke, or elſe he would bruſt.</l>
                  <l>Thus I bid him farewell till next we doe meete,</l>
                  <l>And then as cauſe moueth, ſo ſhall we greete.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>IOANE SHARP.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 33. <hi>Line</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> cary, <hi>reade</hi> cutry. p. 36. l. 30 <hi>for</hi> ſincerity, r. ſcurility. p. 38. l. 28. <hi>for</hi> ſomething, r any thing. <hi>Ibid. for</hi> countrey, r. counter. p. 40. l. 5. <hi>for</hi> contempt, r. contention.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
